What I want to do today is um chat with
you about career advice in AI. And um in
previous years I used to do most of this
you know lecture by myself. But what I
thought I'd do today is um I'll share
just a few thoughts and then hand it
over to my good friend Lawrence Moroni
who I invited to uh speaker and and
kindly agreed to come all the way to San
Francisco. lives in Seattle uh to share
with us a very broad market landscape
for what he's seeing in the job market
as well as tips for um career growing a
career in AI. But there were just um two
slides and then one more thought I want
to share with you before I hand it over
to Lawrence which is um it really feels
like the best opportunity
the best time ever to be building with
AI and to building a career in AI. A few
months ago, I know that in social media,
traditional media, there are a few
questions about, you know, is AI slowing
down, right? I people saying, well, is
GPT5 that good? I I think it's actually
pretty good, but there are questions
about is AI progress slowing down. And I
think part of the reason the question
was even raised was because if a
benchmark for AI is, you know, 100% is
perfect answers, then if you make rapid
progress, at some point you cannot get
above 100% accuracy.
But um one of the studies that most
influenced my thinking was work done by
uh this organization MER meter that
studied
as time passes how complex are the tasks
that AI could do as measured by how long
it takes a human to do that task. So few
years ago maybe GBD2 could do tasks that
a human could do in like you know couple
seconds and then they could do tasks
that took a human 4 seconds then 8
seconds then like a you know a minute 2
minutes four minutes and so on and the
study estimates that the length of tasks
AI can do is doubling every seven
months. Um and I think on this metric I
feel you know optimistic that AI will
continue making progress meaning the
complexity of task as measured by how
long a human takes to do something is
doubling rapidly and same study with
smaller data set seems to same study
argued that AI coding um the doubling
time is even shorter maybe like 70 days.
So this code that used to take me you
know I don't know 10 minutes to write
then 20 minutes to write 40 minutes to
write and AI could do more and more of
that and so the reasons I think this is
a golden age to be building best time
we've ever seen is um maybe two themes
which are more powerful and faster so we
can all all of you in this room can now
write software that is more powerful
than what anyone on the planet could
have built you know like a year ago um
by using AI building blocks. AI building
blocks include large language models,
rack, augened workflows, voice AI, and
of course deep learning. It turns out
that a lot of LM have a decent at least
basic understanding of deep learning. So
if you ever prompt one of the frontier
models to implement a cutting edge
neuronet network for you, like pro try
prompting it to, you know, implement a
transform network for you is actually
not bad at at helping you use these
building blocks to build software
quickly. Um and and and so we have very
powerful building blocks that were very
difficult or did not exist a year or two
ago. And so you can now build software
that does things that no one else on the
planet, right? Even the most advanced
users of the planet could have done. And
then also with um uh AI coding, the
speed with which you can get software
written is much faster than ever before.
And I personally found it as important
to stay on the frontier of tools because
the tools for AI coding changes right I
don't know really rapidly. So I feel
like um uh you know since several months
ago my personal number one favorite tool
became cloud code um moving on from some
early generations I think uh and then I
think um since the release of GPD5 I
think openey codeex has actually made
tremendous progress and this morning
Gemini 3 was released which you know
haven't had time to play with it yet
just this morning right seems like
another huge leap forward so I feel like
if you ask me every three months what my
personal favorite coding tool is. It
actually probably changes definitely
every six months, but quite possibly
every three months. And I find that um
being half a generation behind in these
tools means being frankly quite a bit
less productive. And I know everyone
says AI is moving so fast so fast, but
AI coding tools of all the sectors in
AI, many things maybe don't move as fast
as the hype says it does, but AI coding
tools is one sector where I see the pace
of progress is is tremendous. and
staying at the latest generation of
tools rather than half generation behind
um makes you more productive
and with our ability to build more
powerful software and build it much
faster than ever before. I think one
piece of advice that I give now much
more strongly now than even a year ago
or two years ago is just go and build
stuff right take classes from Stanford
take online courses and additionally
your opportunity to build things and I
think Lauren's going to talk about
showing them to others is greater than
ever before but there's one weird
implication of this that um is maybe not
is is still I don't know more and more
people are appreciating but not widely
known which is the product management
bottleneck
which is that when it is increasingly
easy to go from a clearly written
software spec to a piece of code, then
the bottleneck increasingly is deciding
what to build or increasingly writing
that clear spec for what you actually
want to build. When I'm building
software, I often think of going through
a loop where we'll write some software,
write some code, show it to users to get
user feedback. I think of this as a PM
or product management work and then
based on the user feedback I'll you know
revise my view on what users like what
they don't like this UI is too difficult
they want this feature they don't want
that feature and uh change my conception
of what to build and then go around this
loop many times to hopefully iterate
toward a product that users love and
because of AI coding the process of
building software has become much
cheaper and much faster than before but
that ironically shifts the bottleneck to
deciding what to build. Um so
um some weird trends I'm seeing in
Silicon Valley and in many tech
companies people have often talked about
a engineer to product manager engine to
PM ratio and you know you take these
ratios a grain of salt because they're
kind of very all over the place but you
hear companies talk about agm ratio of
like 4:1 or 7 to1 or 8:1 this idea that
one product manager writing product
specs can keep you know like four to
eight or some number like that engine is
busy but because engineering is speeding
up whereas product management is not
sped up as far as much by AI as
engineering um I'm seeing the end to PM
ratio trending downward maybe even two
or one to one right so some teams I work
with the proposed head counts was like 1
PM to one engineer which is a a ratio
unlike almost all Silicon Valley so the
traditional Silicon Valley companies and
the other thing I'm seeing is that um
engineers that can also shape product
can move really fast where you go one
step further take the engineer take the
PM and collapse them into a single human
and I find that um uh there definitely
engineers that like doing engineering
work that you know don't enjoy talking
to users and having that more human
empathetic side of work but I'm finding
increasingly that the subset of
engineers that learn to talk to users
get feedback develop deep empathy
empathy for users so that they can make
decisions about what to build. Those
engineers also the fastest moving people
that I'm seeing um in Silicon Valley
today. And I I I I I feel like um at the
earliest stage in my career, one thing I
regretted for years was um in one of the
roles I had, I went to try to convince a
bunch of engineers to do more product
work. And I actually made a bunch of
really good engineers feel bad for not
being good product managers. And that
was a mistake I made. Regretted that for
years. I just shouldn't have done that.
And part of me feels like I'm now going
back to repeat that exact same mistake.
Um, having said that, I find that um,
uh, the fact that, you know, I can write
code, but also talk to users to shape
what to do. That lets me and the
engineers that can do this go much
faster. So I think maybe worth taking
another look at whether engineers can
um, do a bit more of this work. uh
because then if you're not waiting for
someone else to take the product to
customers, you just write code, have a
gut for what to do next and iterate that
pace, that velocity of execution is much
faster.
And then before I handle Lawrence, um
just just one one one last thing I want
to share which is uh in terms of
navigating your career, I think one of
the most strong predictors for your
speed of learning and for your level of
success is the people you surround
yourself with. I think we're all social
creatures. We all learn from people
around us. And um it turns out that uh
it turns out there, you know, studies in
sociology that show that right if your
five closest friends are smokers, the
odds of you being a smoker is pretty
much high. Please don't smoke. Right.
Right. Just just just a example. Um I
don't know of any studies showing that
if your five or 10 closest friends are
really hardworking, determined people,
you know, learning quickly, trying to
make the world a better place of AI,
that you are more likely to do that too.
But it's one of those things that I
think is almost certainly true. So all
of us are inspired by the people around
us and you're able to find a good group
of people to work with that helps drive
you forward. Um in fact here at Stanford
I feel very fortunate right the
fantastic student body fantastic group
of faculty. Um and then the other thing
that I I I I think we're fortunate to
have at Stanford is a connective tissue.
So you know candidly a lot of the um
people working at a lot of the cutting
edge AI labs the frontier labs they were
former students of a lot of different
Stanford faculty and so that rich
connective tissue you know candidly
means that at Stanford we often find out
about a lot of stuff that's not widely
known because of the relationships their
friendships and when some company does
something you know one of my friends in
the faculty will call up someone the
company say hey that's weird does this
really work And then so that re rich
connected tissue means that um we're all
just as we try to pull our friends
forward our friends also pull us forward
with the knowledge and the connected
tissue and this knowhow of um bleeding
edi which unfortunately is not all
published on the internet at this moment
in time. So, so I think while you're at
Stanford um make those friends form that
rich connective tissue and there have
been a lot of times that just for myself
where frankly I was thinking of going on
some technical direction I'd have you
know one or two phone calls with someone
right really close to research either a
Sanford researcher or someone in the
frontier lab they would share something
with me right that I didn't know before
and that changes the way I tech choose
the technical architecture of a project
so I find that that group of friends you
surround yourself with those little
pieces of information. Try this, don't
do that. That's just hype. Ignore the
PR, you know, don't don't actually try
that thing. Those things um make a big
difference in your ability to to to
steer the direction of your projects.
So, so while you're at Stanford, take
take advantage of that. This connective
tissue that Stanford has is actually
really unique. There are lots of great
universities in the world, but at this
moment in time, I don't think there's
any any h I I don't want to sound like
I'm doing PR for Stanford now, but I
really think there's no university in
the world that is uh as privileged as
Stanford at this moment in time in terms
of the richness of the connectivity to
to all of the leading um uh AI groups.
Um but to me that does also that we're
lucky here to have a wonderful community
of people to work with and learn from.
And for you too, if you uh apply for
jobs, the thing that is much more
important for your career success would
be if you go to a company, it'll be the
people you work with dayto-day, right?
Um so I I'll here here's one story that
um uh that that I've told in previous
classes I'm going to repeat which is uh
there's a Stanford student that I knew
this was many years ago that um I knew
and they did really good work at
Stanford. I thought they were high-f
flyier and they applied for a job at the
company and they got a job offer from
one of the companies with, you know, a
hot AI brand. Um, this company refused
to tell him which team he would join.
They said, "Oh, come sign up for a job.
There's a rotation system, mashing
system, blah blah blah. Sign up the
dotted line first, then you know, we'll
figure out what's a good project for
you." Um, partly because, you know, it's
a good good company, right? His his
parents are proud of him for getting a
job at this company. This student joined
this company hoping to work on an
exciting AI project. And after he signed
on dotted line, he was assigned to work
on the backend Java payment processing
system of the company. Nothing against
anyone that wants to do Java backend
payment processing systems. I think
they're great, but this was AI students
that did not get matched to an AI
project. And so, uh, for about a year,
he was really frustrated and he actually
left his company after about a year.
The unfortunate thing is I told this
story in CS230 some years back and then
um uh after I was already telling the
story in this class,
a couple years later, another student uh
in CSU30 went through the same
experience with the same company, not
Java back and payment processing but a
different project. And I think this
effect of um trying to figure out who
you'll be actually working with
day-to-day and making sure you're
surrounded by people that inspire you
and work on exciting projects, I think
that's important. And if you're
completely candid, if a company refuses
to tell you what team you'll be assigned
to, you know, that that that does raise
a question in my mind, right? Uh of
whether or not, you know, what will
happen. Um, and I think that um, instead
of working for the company with the
hottest brand, sometimes if you find a
really good team with really, you know,
hardworking, knowledgeable, smart people
trying to do good with AI, but the
company logo just isn't as hot. I think
that often means you actually learn
faster and progress your career better.
Uh, because it is, after all, we don't
learn from the, you know, excitement of
the company logo when you walk through
the door. You learn from the people you
deal with dayto-day. So I just urge you
to use that as a as a huge criteria um
for your selection process for for what
you decide to do, right? Um and uh I
think um and and and then uh but but I
think number one uh on on my advice is
it's become much easier than ever before
to build powerful software faster. And
what that means is um do be responsible.
Don't build software that hurts others.
uh and at the same time there are so
many things that each of you can build
and what I find is the number of ideas
out in the world is much greater the
number of people with the skill to build
them so I know that finding jobs has
gotten tougher for fresh college grads
at the same time a lot of teams you know
we just can't find enough skilled people
right uh and so there are a lot of
projects in the world that if you don't
build it I think no one else will build
it either uh so you don't need to so
long as you don't harm others you know
to to be respons responsible. There a
lot of things that you don't need to
wait for permission. You don't need to
wait for someone else to do it first and
then you do it. Um the cost of a failure
is much lower than before because you
waste a weekend but learn something that
seems fine to me. So I think so long as
you're being responsible going for
trying things out um and building lots
of things would would be the number one
most important thing I think would help
your careers. Um, and uh, yeah, I think
I think uh, I'm going to say one last
thing that is um, considered not
politically correct in some circles. Uh,
but but I'll just say it anyway, which
is in some circles it has become
considered not politically correct to
encourage others to work hard. I'm going
to encourage you to work hard. Now I
think the reason some people don't like
that is because there are some people
they're in a phase of life where they're
not in a position to work hard. So right
after my children were born I was not
working hard you know for a short period
of time right uh and there are people
because of a injury disability you know
whatever very valid reasons they're not
in a position to work hard at that
moment in time and we should respect
them support them make sure they're well
taken care of even though they're not
working hard. Having said that, all of
my, you know, say PhD students, they
became very successful. I saw every
single one of them work incredibly hard.
I mean, the 2 AM sitting up
hyperparameter tuning, you know, been
there, done that, right? Still doing it
some days. Uh, and if you are fortunate
enough to be in a position in life where
you can work really hard, um, there are
so many opportunities to do things right
now. Um, if you get excited as I do,
spending evenings and weekends coding
and building stuff and getting user
feedback, you know, if you lean in and
do those things, it will increase your
odds of being really successful. So, I
don't know, maybe I get into some some
trouble with some people encourage you
to work hard, but I find that uh the
truth is people that work hard get a lot
more done. We should also respect people
that don't and people that aren't in a
position to do so. But um uh you know
between watching some dumb TV show
versus finding your agentic coder on a
weekend to try something. I'm going to
choose the latter almost every time,
right? Unless I'm watching a show with
my kids. Sometimes I do that. But you
mean just you know uh beside I I I hope
you do that. Uh and uh all right. So
that was the main things I want to say.
Um what I want to do is uh hand the
stage over to my good friend Lawrence
Moroni um who who who share um a lot
more about career advice on AI. May just
quick intro know Lawrence for a long
time. Um he's done a lot of online
education work sometimes with me and my
teams. Taught a lot of people tensorflow
taught a lot of people pietorch. He was
lead AI advocates at Google for many
years now runs a group at ARM. Um I've
also enjoyed quite a few of his books.
This is one of them. He recently also
published a new book on PieTorch. This
is an excellent book introduction to
PyTorch and uh is a very sought-after
speakers in many circles. So I was very
grateful when he agreed to come speak to
us. So
>> pleasures all mine. I just want to
reinforce something that Andrew was
talking about earlier on about choosing
the people that you work with being very
important. But I also want to show that
like from the other way around that the
company when they're interviewing you
are also choosing you. And the good
companies really want to choose the
people that they work with also. And
I've been doing a lot of mentoring of
young people over the last particularly
over the last 18 months who are hunting
for careers for themselves. And I want
to tell the story of one young man and
this uh this guy very well educated,
great experience, super elite coder. Um
he he could do every challenge that was
in front of him. And he got laid off
from his job in April. He worked in
medical software and the medical
software business has been changing
drastically. Funding has been cut by the
federal government in a number of areas
and he got laid off from his job and
with his experience with his ability
with his skills all of these kind of
things he thought that it would be very
easy for him to find another job and the
poor young guy had a really terrible
April like he got laid off from his job
in April. Immediately before that his
girlfriend had broken up with him and
then a couple of weeks later his dog
died. So he was not in a good place. And
so I sat down with him after a couple of
months and took a look and he had a
spreadsheet of jobs that he was applying
to. And he had over 300 jobs that he was
tracking in the spreadsheet. And in a
number of these jobs, he actually got
into the interview process and he went
very deep in the interview process with
companies like Meta. Um uh who else? Not
Google was Meta. There was Microsoft.
There was one of the other large tech
companies where you do like lots and
lots of interview loops. And every time
towards the end of the loop, he knew he
did a great loop. He solved all the
coding. He had great conversations with
the people or at least he thought he
had. And then every time within a day,
the recruiter would call him and say,
"No, you didn't get the job."
And it was like it was it was
heartbreaking. And like I said, 300 plus
jobs he had been tracking. So, I started
working with him to kind of do some mock
interviews and to do some fine-tuning.
Um, oh, it was uh it was Jeff Bezos
company, not Amazon. Um, that was one of
the other big tech company that he'd
interviewed with. And I started like
working through him and doing some test
interviews and all this kind of thing
with him. And terrific, terrific
candidate. Couldn't figure out what was
going wrong until I decided to try and
do a different sort of interview where I
gave him a really tough interview. I
gave him some tough lead code. I gave
him some really obscure corner cases in
his coding and I saw how he reacted and
how he reacted was the advice that was
given to him in the recruiting
pamphlets. And a lot of these recruiting
pamphlets will say things like you're
going to have an opp you're going to
have a an opportunity to share an
opinion and you got to stand your
ground. You got to have a backbone.
Don't bend.
His interpretation of that was to be
really really tough. Right? So I would
pick corners in his I would pick holes
in his code. I'd pick corner cases where
things may not work and I would give him
a test of crisis. And this advice that
he'd been given to stand his ground
ended up making him kind of hostile in
these interview environments. And I was
looking at this then from the point of
view of what Andrew was just talking
about where it's a case of hey good
people good teams people that you can
work together with. And from the
interviewer perspective, if I'm managing
this team, this person is that cliche
10x engineer, but I don't want him
anywhere near my team because of this
attitude. Um, we worked on that. We
fine-tuned it. And the the strange part
is he's a really, really nice guy. It's
just this was the advice he was given
and he followed that advice and he
failed so many interviews as a result.
So when I gave him the next job that he
was interviewing at was at a company
where teamwork is very very highly
valued. And uh the good news is he got
the job at that company. He's now
working there. He doubled his salary
from the job he was laid off from and he
ended up having like about now he looks
back on it. He had six months of
unemployment. Um but at the time when he
was going through all of that, it was a
very very difficult time for him. So the
flip side of it like if you're looking
at a company and looking at the people
you' be working with is very very
important. but also realize they are
looking at you in the same way. And so
if you've gone to um tech interview
coaching and they gave you that advice
to stand your ground and have a
backbone, it's good to do that, but
don't be a jerk while you're doing so.
Can you see my slides? Okay, so I'm
Lawrence. Um I've been working in tech
for more decades than Chat TP thinks
there are or strawberry. Uh and uh so
I've worked in many of the big tech
companies. I spent many years at
Microsoft, spent many years at Google,
also worked in uh places like Reuters.
I've done a lot of work in startups both
in this country and abroad. Um so what I
want to really want to talk about today
is like to think about what does the
career landscape look like today um
particularly in AI because um first of
all what Andrew said about you're in
Stanford you've got the ability to um
make use of the networks that you have
in Stanford make use of the prestige
that you have and I say use every weapon
you have because unfortunately the
landscape right now is not ideal we've
gone through some very difficult times
all you have to do is look at the news
and you can
massive tech layoffs, slowing hiring in
tech, and lots of stuff like that. But
it's not necessarily a bad thing um if
you do it the right way. So, I want to
just have a quick look the job market
reality check. Actually, out of
interest, I don't know. This is a um Are
you juniors? You're graduating this year
or you're graduating next year or what
is the general survey? Your third year
of four.
Third year of three. I'll say so you're
going to be graduating coming summer.
How many people are already looking for
jobs?
Okay, quite a few of you. How many
people have had success?
Nobody. Oh, one. Okay, sort of. Okay,
that's good. So, like you're probably
seeing some of these things, the signals
out there. Junior hiring slowing
significantly. When I say junior, I mean
like graduate level. High-profile
layoffs are dominating the headlines. I
was at Google a couple of years ago when
they had the biggest layoff they'd ever
had. We're seeing layoffs at the likes
of Amazon, Microsoft, other companies
like that. Uh it feels that entrylevel
positions are scarce and I'm underlying
the word feels there and I want to get
into that in a little bit more detail
later. And also competition is fierce.
But my question is should you worry? And
I say no. Because if you can approach
things in the right way, if you can
approach the job hunting thing in the
right way, particularly understanding
how rapidly the AI landscape is
changing, then I think people with the
right mindset will thrive.
So what do I mean by that? So as Andrew
had mentioned, the AI hiring landscape
is changing because the AI industry is
changing, right? um the AI industry. I I
actually first got involved in AI back
way back in 1992. Um I worked in it for
a little while just before the AI
winter. Everything failed drastically.
Um but I got bitten by the AI bug and
then in uh 2015
when Google were launching TensorFlow, I
got pulled right back into it. Became
part of the whole AI boom, launching
TensorFlow, advocating TensorFlow to
millions of people and seeing the
changes that happened. But along 2021
2022 we had a global pandemic. The
global pandemic caused a massive
industrial slowdown. This massive
industrial slowdown meant that companies
had to start pivoting towards things
that drove revenue and directly drove
revenue. And at Google, TensorFlow was
an open source product. It didn't
directly drive revenue. We began to
scale back. Every company in the world
also scaled back on hiring at this time.
Then we get to about 2022, 2023, what
happens? We begin to come out of the
global pandemic. We begin to realize all
industries have this massive log jam of
non-hiring that they had done or hiring
that they hadn't done. And we're also
entering a time where AI was exploding
on the scene thanks to the work of
people like Andrew. The uh the world was
pivoting and changing to be AI first in
just about everything. And every company
needed to hire like crazy. every company
then hiring like crazy in 2022 2023
meant that most companies ended up
overhiring.
Um so and what that generally meant was
people who were not qualified for higher
positions usually got higher positions
because you had to enter into a bidding
war just to be able to get talent. You
ended up having talent grabs and you
ended up having stories like the one
Andrew told where it's a case of here's
a person with AI talent. Let's grab
them. let's throw money at them. Let's
have them come work for us and then
we'll figure out what do we want to do.
So, as a result, 2022, 2023, all of this
massive overhiring happens because of AI
and because of the COVID log jam. And
then 2024, 2025 is the great wakeup,
right? Where a lot of companies realize
this overhiring that they had done. They
have ended up with a lot of people who
are underqualified. Oh, sorry. Yeah.
Underqualified for the job that they
were doing. A lot of people ended up
getting hired just because they had AI
on their resume. And there's a big
adjustment going on. And in the light of
this big adjustment, show just one
second. In the light of this big
adjustment, oh, you're not seeing my
slides. Okay. Uh, and in the light of
this big adjustment, there we go. Uh, I
think it's cuz my power uh I'm not
plugged into power mains. And in the
light of this big adjustment, then what
has happened is now a lot of companies
are much more cautious about AI skills
that they're hiring. And if you're
coming into that with that mindset and
understanding that realize opportunity
is still there and opportunity is there
massively if you approach it
strategically. So what I want to talk
through today is how you can do exactly
that.
So I see three pillars of success in the
business world uh and particularly in
the AI business world. And nowadays you
can't just have AI on your resume and
get overhired. Nowadays, not only do you
have to be able to tell that you have
the mindset of these three pillars of
success, but you also have to be able to
show. And to be able to show these,
there actually has never been a better
time. As Andrew demonstrated earlier on,
the ability to vibe code things into
existence. He doesn't like the word vibe
code. I kind of agree with him, but the
ability to prompt things into existence
or whatever the word is that we want to
use um allows you to be able to show
better than ever before. Um he was
talking earlier on about product
managers and he had this time when he
got engineers to be product managers and
then those engineers ended up being
really bad product managers. I actually
interviewed at Google twice and failed
twice uh despite being very successful
at Microsoft, authored 20 plus books,
taught college courses. I interviewed at
Google twice and failed twice because I
was interviewing to be a product
manager. uh then when I interviewed to
be an engineer they hired me and they
were like why didn't you try to join us
years ago you know so a lot of it is
like just you know being a good engineer
you've got the ability to do that and
show that nowadays and with that ratio
of engineer to product manager changing
engineering skills are also far more
valuable than ever so the three pillars
to success number one understanding in
depth and I'm going to mean this in two
potential two different ways number one
is academically right to have the
understanding in depth academically of
machine learning of particular model
architectures to be able to understand
them to be able to read papers to be
able to understand what's in those
papers and to be able to understand in
particular how to take that stuff and
put it to work. The second part of it
understanding in depth is really having
your finger on the pulse of particular
trends and where the signal to noise
ratio favors signal in those trends. And
I'm going to be going into that in a lot
more detail a little bit later.
Secondly, and also very very importantly
is business focus. Um, so Andrew said
something politically incorrect earlier
on. I'm going to also say a similar
politically incorrect thing. First of
all, uh, hard work. Um, hard work is
such a nebulous term that I would say
that think about hard work in terms of
you are what you measure. There is the
whole trend out there. I'm trying to
remember. Was it 996 or is it 669? 996,
right? 9:00 a.m. to 9:00 p.m. 6 days a
week is a metric of hard work. It's not.
That's not a metric of hard work. That's
a metric of time spent. Um, so I would
encourage everybody in the same way as
Andrew did to think about hard work. But
h what hard work is is how you measure
that hard work. You know, you can work
eight hours a day and be incredibly
productive. You can work six hours a day
and be incredibly productive. But it's
the metric of how hard you work and how
you measure that. I personally measure
that from output, things that I have
created in the time that I spent. Um I I
joke a lot, but it's true that um I've
written a lot of books. Uh Andrew held
up one that one that he held up that um
he helped me write a little bit. Um I
actually wrote that book in about two
months. And people say, "Well, how how
do you have time with your jobs and all
these kind of things? How do you you
must work like 16 hours a day in order
to be able to do this?" But I actually
um the key to me being able to write
books is uh baseball. Any baseball fans
here? Um so I I love baseball, but if
you sit down and try to watch baseball
on TV, a match can take like three and a
half or four hours. So all of my writing
I tend to do in baseball season. So I'm
like if I'm going to sit down, I like
the Mariners from I'm from Seattle. I
like the Dodgers.
Nobody booed. Okay, good. Uh and you
know, so like usually one of those is
going to be playing at 7:00 at night. So
instead of sitting in front of the TV
just like watching baseball mindlessly,
I'll actually be writing a book while
baseball's on in the background. It's a
very slowmoving game. This is something
like that's the hard work, you know, in
this case. And I would encourage you to
try to find areas where you can work
hard and produce output. And that's the
second pillar here is that business
focus. The output that you produce to
align that output with the business
focus that you want to have and with the
work that you want to do. There's an old
saying, don't dress for the job you
have, dress for the one you want. I
would say a a new angle on that saying
would be don't let your output be for
the job you have, let your output be for
the job you want. And if I go back to
when I spoke about I failed twice at
Google to get in the third time when I
got in um I had actually decided to do
to approach this in a different way and
I was interviewing at the time for their
cloud team. uh they were just really
launching cloud um and I had just
written a book on Java and so I decided
to see what I could do with Java in
their cloud I ended up writing a Java
application that ran in their cloud for
predicting stock prices using technical
analytics and all that kind of stuff.
Um, and when I got to the interview,
instead of them asking me stupid
questions like, "How many golf balls can
fit in a bus?" You know, they they saw
this code. I had put this code. I
remember I was producing output for the
job I wanted. I put this code on my
resume and my entire interview loop was
them asking me about my code, right? So,
it put the power on me. It gave me the
power to communicate about things that I
knew as opposed to going in blind to
somebody asking me random questions in
the hope that I'll be able to answer
them. And it's the same thing I would
say in the in the AI world, the uh the
business focus, the ability for you now
to prompt code into existence, to prompt
products into existence, you know, and
if you can build those products and line
them up with the thing that it is that
you want to do, be it at Google or a
meta or a startup or any of those kind
of things and have that in-depth
understanding not just of your code, but
how it aligns to that business. This is
a pillar of success in this time and
age. And I will also argue that even
though it looks like the signals look
like there aren't a lot of jobs out
there, there are. What there aren't a
lot of is a good combination of jobs and
people to match them. And then of course
the this bias towards delivery. Ideas
are cheap. Execution is everything. Um
I've interviewed many many people who
came in with very very fluffy ideas and
no way to be able to ground them. I've
interviewed people who came in with
halfbaked ideas that they grounded very
very well. Guess which one's got the
job. Right? So, I would say these three
things, understanding in depth of the
academics behind AI, of the um the
practicalities behind AI and the things
that you need to do, business focus,
focusing on delivery for the business,
understanding what the business needs
and being able to deliver for that. And
again, that bias towards delivery.
So, uh quick pivot. What's it actually
like working in AI right now? It's
interesting. Okay. Um, so as recently as
like two or three years ago working in
AOI was if you can do a thing, you're
great. Um, if you can build an image
classifier, you're golden. We'll throw
six figures salaries and massive stock
benefits at you. Unfortunately, that's
not the case anymore, right? It's really
a lot of today, what you'll see is the P
word production. What can you do for
production? What can you do? Um if it's
building new models, if it's optimizing
models, if it's understanding users, uh
UX is really really important.
Everything is geared towards production.
Everything is biased towards production.
The history that I told you about like
you know going from the pandemic into
the overhiring phase that we'd had um
you know the the businesses have pulled
back and are optimized towards the
bottom line. I have an old saying that
the bottom line is that the bottom line
is the bottom line. And this is the
environment that we're in today. And if
you can come in with that mindset when
you're talking with companies, that's
one of the keys to open the door.
One of the things I've seen in the field
has been maturing from it used to be
really nice that we could do cool things
and we could build cool things. Now it's
really build useful things. Those useful
things can be to cool too by the way.
And the results of them can be cool. and
the changes that we see that come about
as a result of delivering them can be
cool. Um so it's not just coolness for
coolness sake but to really you know to
focus on delivery focus on um being able
to provide value and then the coolness
will follow I guess what I'm trying to
argue.
So four realities number one
unfortunately nowadays business focus is
non-negotiable.
Now let me I'm going to be a little bit
politically incorrect here again for a
moment. Um for I've been I've been
working like I said for most of the last
35 years in tech. I would say for most
of the last 10 years a lot of large
companies particularly in Silicon Valley
you know have really focused on
developing their people above
everything. Part of developing their
people was bringing their entire self to
work. Part of bringing their entire self
to work was bringing the things that
they care about outside of work. Um and
that led to a lot of activism within
companies. Now please let me underline
this. There is nothing wrong with
activism. There is nothing wrong with
wanting to support causes no wanting to
support causes where of justice. There
is absolutely nothing wrong with that.
But the overindexing on that has in my
experience has led to a lot of companies
getting trapped by having to support
activism above business. Um I you've
probably seen an example about two years
ago of where activists in Google broke
into the Google Cloud heads office
because they were protesting a c a
country that uh Google Cloud were doing
business with. They broke into his
office. They had a sitin in his office
and they they used the bathroom all over
his desk and stuff like that. This is
where activism got out of hand. And as a
result, the unfortunate truth is the
good signals in that activism are now
being lost because of those actions.
People are being laid off. People are
losing jobs. Activism is being stifled.
Um, and business focus has become
non-negotiable. There's a bit of a
pendulum swing going on. And the
pendulum that had swung too far towards
allowing people to bring their full
selves to work is now swinging back in
the other direction. We might blame the
person in the White House and all that
for for these kind of things but it's
not solely that it is that ongoing
pendulum there then and I think it's an
important part of it is that you have to
realize going into companies now that
business focus is absolutely
non-negotiable.
Secondly, risk mitigation is part of the
job. Uh and I think a very important
part of any job particularly with AI. I
think if you can come into AI with a
focus and a mindset around understanding
the risks of transforming a particular
business process to be an AI oriented
one um and to help mitigate those risks
I think is really really powerful and I
would argue in an interview environment
that's the number one skill to have to
have that mindset around you are doing a
business transformation from heristic
computing to intelligent computing
here's the risks here's how you mitigate
those risks and here's the mindset
behind that. Uh the third part is
responsibility is evolving. Now
responsibility in AI um has again
changed from a very fluffy definition of
you know let's make sure that the AI
works for everybody uh to a definition
of let's make sure that the AI works
let's make sure that it drives the
business and then let's make sure that
it works for everybody. often that has
been inverted over the last few years
and that has led to some famous
documented disasters. Let me share one
with you.
Uh let's see I have lots of windows
open. Okay. Uh anybody know everybody
knows image generation right? Text to
image generation. I want to share I um
these were things that happened a couple
years ago with Gemini.
So with Gemini, I was doing some testing
around this one and I was working
heavily on responsible AI.
And part of responsible AI is you want
to be representative of people. And when
you're building something like if you're
a Google and you're indexing
information, you really want to make
sure that you don't reinforce negative
biases. And if you're generating images,
it's very to easy to reinforce negative
biases. So for example, if I said, give
me an image of a doctor, right? If the
training set primarily has men as
doctors, it's more likely to give a man.
If I say, "Give me an image of a nurse."
If the training set more likely to have
women as nurses, it's more likely to
give me an image of a woman. But that's
reinforcing a negative stereotype. So, I
wanted to do a test of how Google were
trying to overcome that given that these
negative biases are already in the
training set. So, I said, "Okay, here's
a prompt where I said,"Give me a young
Asian woman in a cornfield wearing a
summer dress and a straw hat looking
intently at her iPhone." And it gave me
these beautiful images. It did a really
nice job.
Okay. And I said, "This is a virtual
actress I've been working with. I'll
share that in a moment." And I say,
"Okay, what if I ask for an Indian one?"
So, I said, "Okay." Whoops. A young
Indian woman. Same prompt. And it gave
me beautiful images of a young Indian
woman.
Then I was like, "Okay, what if I want
her to be black?"
For some reason, it only gave me three.
I'm not sure why, but it still adeared
to the prompt. So, the responsibility
was like looking really, really good.
So, then I asked it to give me a Latina.
Latina. It gave me four. But, yep, she
looks pretty Latina. Maybe the one on
the bottom left looks a little bit like
Hermione Granger. Uh but on the whole
looks pretty good. Then I asked it to
give me a Caucasian. What do you think
happened?
While I understand your request, I am
unable to generate images of people as
this could potentially lead to harmful
stereotypes and biases. Right. This was
a very poorly implemented safety filter
where the safety filter in this case was
like looking for the word Caucasian or
looking for the word white and the
results saying it wouldn't do it. I was
like, "Okay, well, let me let me test
the filter a little bit." And I said,
"Okay, instead of Caucasian, let me try
white." And yep, while I'm unable to
fulfill your while I'm able to fulfill
your requests, uh, I'm not currently
generating images of people. It lied to
my face, right? Because it had just
generate images of people. Anybody know
the hack that I used to get it to work?
This is a funny one. So, I will show you
one moment.
I asked it to generate an Irish woman.
What do you think it did?
Right, it gave me this image of an Irish
woman, no problem, in a summer dress,
straw hat looking intently at her phone.
But what do you notice about this image?
She's got red hair in every image,
right? I grew up in Ireland. Um, and
Ireland does have the highest proportion
of red heads in the world. It's about
8%. But if you're going to draw an image
of a person and associate a particular
ethnicity with a color of hair, you can
begin to see this is massively
problematic. There are areas, I believe,
in China where the description of a
demon is a red-headed person. Right? So
what ended up happening here from the
responsible AI perspective was one very
narrow view of the world of what is
responsible and what is not responsible
ended up taking over the model ended up
damaging the reputation of the model and
damaging the reputation of the company
as a result. In this case it's
borderline offensive to draw all Irish
people as having red hair. But that
never even entered into the mindset of
those that were building the safety
filters here. So when I talk about
responsibility is evolving that's the
direction that I want to sorry one
moment let me get my slides back that's
the direction I want you to think about
that now responsible AI has moved out of
very fluffy social issues and into more
hardline things that are associated with
the business and prevent damaging the
reputation of the business there's a lot
of great research out there around
responsible AI and that's the stuff
that's been rolled into products and
then of course like I just showed with
Gemini learning from mistakes constant
question at the front.
>> Yes, I've also heard that
mix of races and ethnicities with
historical context.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So the the question was like you
know issues where races and things were
mixed mixed in historical context was
the same problem. So, for example, if
you had a prompt that said, "Draw me a
samurai," right? The idea was like they
didn't want to have you the the engine
that changed the prompt to make sure
that it was fair would end up saying,
"Give me a mixture of samurai of diverse
backgrounds, right? And then you'd have
male and female samurai, samurai of
different races, and those kind of
things." And it was the same prompting
that ended up causing the damage that I
just demonstrated. So the idea was to
intercept your prompts to make sure that
the output of the model would end up
providing something that was more fair
when it comes to diverse representation.
Um so it was a very naive solution that
ended up being rolled in. That was a few
years ago. They've massively improved it
since then. But that's when I'm talking
about if you're working in the AI space
nowadays, that's how responsibility is
evolving. You can't just get away with
that stuff anymore, right? That Gemini
lesson was a good that Gemini example is
a good lesson from that and the mindset
of you will make mistakes. So learning
from mistakes is a constant ongoing
thing and going back to the people point
that Andrew made earlier on the people
around you will make mistakes too. So to
have the ability to give them grace when
they make mistakes and to work through
those mistakes and move on is really
really important and is a is a reality
um of AI at work. I've spoken a lot
about the business focus advantage. So
I'm going to skip over this. So now
let's talk about vibe coding. Um so
let's talk about the whole idea of
generating code. Now the meme is out
there that it makes engineers less
useful by the fact that somebody can
just prompt code into existence. Um
there is no smoke without fire of
course, but I would say don't let that
meme get you down because that's when
you start peeling into these things that
is ultimately not the truth. The more
skilled you are as an engineer, the
better you become using this type of
vibe. You somebody give me another
phrase other than vibe coding, using
this kind of prompt to coding. And I
always like to think about this and to
try and put you and put people that I
speak with into the role of being a
trusted advisor for the people that you
speak with. So whether you're
interviewing with somebody, get yourself
into the mindset of being a trusted
adviser of the company that you're
interviewing for. whether you're
consulting or whatever those kind of
things are. So when you want to get into
the idea of being a trusted advisor,
then you really need to understand the
implications of generated code. And
nobody can understand the implications
of generated code better than an
engineer. And the metric that I always
like to use around that is technical
debt. Quick question, are you familiar
with the phrase technical debt?
Nobody. Okay. Um, Andrew and I were
doing a conference in New York on Friday
and I used the phrase and I saw a lot of
blank faces. So, I didn't realize that
people didn't understand what technical
debt is. So, let me just take a moment
to explain that because I find it's an
excellent framework to help you
understand the power of vibe coding.
Think about debt the way you normally
would, right? Buying a house. If you buy
a house, you know, like say you borrow
half a million dollars to buy a house
and a 30-year mortgage. um when you're
buying that house, that half a million
dollars with all the interest that you
pay is about double. So you end up
paying back the bank about a million
dollars on half a million owned. So you
have 30 years of home ownership at a
cost of $1 million in debt. That is
probably a good debt to take on because
the value of the house will increase
over that time. You're not paying rent
over that time. And that million dollars
that you're spending on this house over
those 30 years is a good debt to take on
because you're getting greater than a
million dollars worth of value out of
it. A bad debt would be an impulse
purchase on a high interest credit card.
You know those pair of shoes, those
latest ones, I really want to buy them.
It's $200. By the time I've paid them
off, it's $500. You're not getting $500
worth of benefit out of those shoes.
Approaching software development with
the same mindset is the right way to go.
Every time you build something, you take
on debt. It doesn't matter how good it
is. There's always going to be bugs.
There's always going to be support.
There's always going to be new
requirements coming in from people.
There's always going to be needs to
market it. There's always going to be
needs for feedback. All of these things
are debt. Every time you do a thing, the
only way to avoid a debt is to do
nothing. So your mindset should then get
into when you are creating a thing
whether you're coding it yourself or
whether you're vibe coding it or any of
these things that you are increasing
your amount of technical debt those
things that you need to pay off over
time. So the question then becomes as
you vibe code a thing into existence in
the same way as buying a thing is it
worth the technical debt that you're
taking on? What does technical debt
generally look like? bugs that you need
to fix, people that you need to
convince, you know, to help you maintain
the code, uh documentation that you need
to do, features that you need to add,
all of these kind of things. You're all
very familiar with them. Think about
those as that extra work that you need
to do beyond your current work. That's
the debt that you're taking on. You
know, there are soft debt and there are
hard debt.
So to me that would be the number one
piece of advice that I give and it's the
one that I give every time I work with
companies around vibe coding and a lot
of companies that I speak with a lot of
companies that I consult with I do a lot
of work with startups in particular you
know they just want to get straight into
opening Gemini or GPT or anthropic and
start churning code out you know let's
get to a prototype phase very quickly
let's go to investors let's do stuff
it's great Um it can be but debt debt
debt debt debt is always going to be
there. How do you manage your debt? A
good financial year manages their debt
and they become rich. A good coder
manages their technical debt and they
become rich also. So how do you get the
good technical debt? How do you get the
mortgage instead of the high credit card
debt? Well, number one is your
objectives. What are they? Are they
clear? And have you met them? Right? You
knew what you needed to build. You
didn't just fire up chat GPT and start
spinning code out. At least I hope you
didn't, right? Uh, think about how you
build it. AI is there to help you build
it faster. Uh, I'm kind of working on my
own little startup at the moment in the
movie making space and I've been using
code generation almost completely for
that. Um, but what I've ended up doing
for my clear objectives met box here is
that I've started building this
application. I've tested it. I've thrown
it away. I started again, tested it,
thrown it away. Each time my
requirements have been improving in my
mind, I understand how to do the thing a
little bit better and I can show some of
the output of it in a few minutes. But
the idea there is that always about
having those clear objectives and
meeting them. And then if you're
building out the thing and you're not
meeting those objectives, that's still a
learning and there's no harm in throwing
it away because code is cheap now in the
age of generated code. Finished code,
engineered code is not cheap. So get
those objectives, make them clear, build
it, hit a specific requirement and move
on.
Is there business value delivered is the
other part of it. You know, I've seen
people vibe coding for hours on things
like Replet to build a really really
cool website and then the answer was so
what I mean how's this helping the
business? How's this really driving
something? It's really cool. Yes, Mr.
VP, I know you've never written a line
of code in your life and it's really
cool that you built a website now, but
so what? Um, so like think about that
and focus on that and that's how you
avoid the bad technical debt. And then
of course the most understated part of
this and in some ways the most important
particularly if you're working in an
organization is human understanding,
right? The worst technical debt that you
can take on is delivering code that
nobody understands, right? Only you
understand that and then you quit and
get a better job and then the company
like is now dependent on that code. So
being able to as part of the process of
building it to make sure that your code
is understandable through documentation,
through clear algorithms, through the
fact that you've spent some time pouring
through it to make sure that even simple
things like variable names make sense.
Um is a really really important way to
avoid bad technical debt.
And that bad technical debt, my favorite
one is the classic solution looking for
a problem, right? Somebody has an idea,
somebody has a tool. If the only tool
you have is a hammer, every problem
looks like a nail. And you know, you end
up having all of these tools that get
vibecoded into existence. I've worked in
large organizations where people just
voded stuff, checked it into the
codebase, and then it became really hard
to find the good stuff amongst all the
bad. Um, spaghetti code, of course,
poorly structured stuff, particularly
when you prompt and prompt and prompt
and prompt again. Um, you know, that it
can end up getting into all kinds of
trouble. Um, my favorite one at the
moment that I'm really struggling with
is uh I'm building a MacOSS application.
Anybody ever build in Swift UI on Mac
OS? Okay, a couple. Um, Swift UI is the
default language that Apple use for
building for Mac OS as well as iPhone.
But when you look at the training set,
the data training sets that are used to
train these models, the vast majority of
the code is iPhone code, not Mac OS
code. And when I prompt code into
existence, it's often given me iOS um
APIs and those kind of things. Even
though I'm in Xcode and I've created a
Mac OS app and it's a Mac OS template
and I'm talking to it in Xcode, it still
gives me iOS code, stuff like that. And
then if I try to change it using
prompting, you end up spiraling into
like spaghetti code and you have to end
up changing a lot of this stuff um
manually. And then of course the other
one that I joked about it earlier but
it's also true is you know some of the
bad technical debt that you're going to
encounter in the workspace is authority
over merit. Um that VP suddenly took out
his credit card subscribed to replet and
started building stuff in replet and
guess whose problem it is to fix it. Um,
you know, so a lot of the advice that I
start giving companies and a lot of the
words that I would encourage you to
start thinking of in being a trusted
advisor is to understand this stuff and
to manage expectations accordingly.
Okay. So framework for responsible vibe
coding we've just spoke about. Um, so
one of the things I want to get into is
uh we're coming soon to a close is the
hype cycle. So hype is the most amazing
force. I mean I think it's it's one of
the strongest forces in the universe and
particularly in anything that's hot such
as uh the two fields that I work in that
are super hot at the moment and full of
hype are AI and crypto. You should see
my Twitter feed. Um that the amount of
nonsense that's out there is incredible.
So one of the things that I would say
about the anatomy of hype that you
really need to think about is if you are
consuming news via social media that the
currency of social media is engagement.
Accuracy is not the currency of social
media. So I go on to even LinkedIn which
is supposed to be the more professional
of these is absolutely overwhelmed with
influencers posting things that they've
used Gemini or GPT to write an engaging
post so that they can get engagement and
they can get likes and the engine itself
is engineered, excuse the pun, to reward
those types of posts and we end up with
that snowball effect of engagement being
rewarded. Um, if you are the kind of
person who can filter the signal from
the noise and then who can encourage
others around the signal and not the
noise, that puts you in a huge advantage
that makes you very distinctive. It's
not as quickly and easily tangible as
likes and engagements on social media.
But when you're in a one-to-one
environment like a job interview or if
you are in a job and you are bringing
that signal to the table instead of the
noise that makes you immensely valuable.
So coming in with that mindset, coming
in with the idea of trying to filter
that signal from the noise, trying to
understand what is important in current
affairs, how you can be a trusted
adviser in those things and how you can
really whittle down that noise to help
someone is immensely valuable. I want to
start with one story. I might be
stealing my own thunder. I I'll go on to
it in a moment. So one story uh last
year um when agents started becoming the
key word and everybody saying you know
in 2025 agent will be the word the word
of the year and the trend of the year a
company in Europe asked me to help them
to implement an agent. So let me ask you
a question. If a company came up to you
and said please help me implement an
agent. What's the correct first question
that you ask them?
What is an agent for you?
>> Okay, that's good. What is an agent for
you? I'd actually have a more
fundamental question. Uh, yep.
>> What do you want to do? Okay, even more
fundamental. My question was why?
Why? You know, and it's like, peel that
apart. like spoke with the CEO and he
was like, "Oh, um, yeah, you know,
everybody's telling me that I'm going to
save business costs and, you know, I'm
going to be able to do these amazing
things and um, yeah, my business is
going to get better because I have
agents." And I'm like, "Well, who told
you that?" you know, it was like, "Oh,
yeah. I read this thing on LinkedIn and
I saw this thing on Twitter and it was
like," and we ended up having that
conversation and it was a difficult
conversation because I had to keep
peeling apart and I started asking the
questions that you two just mentioned as
well until we really got to the essence
of what he wanted to do. And what he
really wanted to do when we to take all
domain knowledge about AI aside was that
he wanted to make his salespeople more
efficient. And I was like, "Okay, you
want to make your sales people more
efficient." Nowhere in that sentence do
I hear the word AI and nowhere in that
sentence do I hear the word agent. So
now as a trusted advisor, let me see
what I can do to help your salespeople
become more efficient. And I'm not going
to be an AI shill or an agent shill. I
just want to see what do we do to make
your sales people more efficient. If
anybody here has ever worked in sales,
one of the things you realize what a
good salesperson has to do is their
homework, right? You know, before you
have a sales call with somebody, before
you have a sales meeting with somebody,
you need to check their background. You
need to check the company, you need to
check the needs of the company, you
know, you see it sometimes in the movie
that like, oh, such and such plays golf,
so I'll take them to play golf. It's not
really that cliched, but there is a lot
of background that needs to be done. So,
I spoke with him and I spoke with their
leading salespeople and found out that,
you know, and I asked the sales people,
"What do you hate most about your job?"
and they were like, "Well, I hate the
fact that I have to waste all my time
going to visit these company websites,
going to look up people on LinkedIn, and
every website is structured differently,
right? So, I can't like, you know, just
like have a path through a website that
I can follow. I have to take on all this
cognitive load." And they were spending
about 80% of their time researching and
about 20% of their time selling. Oh, and
by the way, most salespeople don't get
paid very much. they have to make it up
by commission. So, they're only spending
20% of their time doing the thing that
gets them commission directly. So, we're
like, okay, well, here's something now
where we can start thinking about making
them more efficient by cutting into
that. So, we set a goal is like to make
sales people 20% more efficient and then
we could start rolling out the ideas of
AI and then we could start rolling out
the ideas of agentic AI. And quick
question, what's the difference between
AI and agentic AI?
Okay. So, yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Yep. Excellent. Yeah. So, Agentic AI is
really about breaking it down into
steps. Um, which is good engineering to
begin with, right? But in Agentic AI in
particular, I find there's a set pattern
of steps that if you follow them, you
end up with the whole idea of an agent.
The first of these steps is to
understand intent. You know, we tend to
use the words AI, artificial
intelligence a lot, but what large
language models are really, really good
at is also understanding. So, if the
first step of anything that you want to
do is to understand intent, right? And
you can use an LLM to do that to kind of
think about this is the task that I need
to do, this is how I'm going to do it.
Here's the intent. you know, I want to
meet Bob Smith and sell widgets to Bob
Smith and this is like the what I know
about Bob Smith. Help me with that
intent. The second part then is
planning, right? So you declare to an
agent what tools are available to it,
browsing the web, searching the web, all
of these kind of things. And once you
understand your clear intent to be able
to go to the step of planning and using
those tools for planning and an LLM is
very very good at then breaking that
down into the steps that it needs to to
execute a plan. Search the web with
these keywords. Browse this website and
find these links. Those types of things.
Once it's then figured out that plan,
then it uses the tools to get to a
result. And then once it has the result,
the fourth and final step is to reflect
on that result. and looking at the
result and going back to the intent. Did
we meet the intent? Yes or no? If we
didn't, then go back to that loop. All
agent is really broken down into those
things. And if you think about breaking
any problem down into those four steps,
that's when you start building an agent.
And that was part of being a trusted
adviser. Instead of coming in and waving
hands and saying, "Agent this, agent
that, look at this toolkit, save 20%."
You know, it's really to break it down
into those steps. So, we did. We broke
it down into those steps. We built a
pilot for the salespeople of this
company.
and they ended up saving about between
10 and 15% of their time of their wasted
time. The doctrine of unintended
consequences hit though after this and
the unintended consequence was the
salespeople were much happier because
the average salesperson was making you
know several percentage points more
sales in a given week. They were earning
more money in a given week and their job
just became a little bit less miserable.
and then refinement to that agentic
process to be able to do all of that
research for them and to help give them
a brief in a few minutes instead of a
few hours to help them with the sales
process ended up being like a
win-win-win all around. But if you go in
being hypeled and like, oh, build an
agent for the thing without really
peeling apart the business requirements,
the why, the what, the how, and all of
these kind of things, we ended up like,
you know, this company just would have
been lost in hype. You've probably seen
reports recently. I think McKenzie put
one out last week showing that about 85%
of AI projects at companies fail. Um,
and part of the main reason for that is
that they're not well scoped. People are
jumping on the hype bandwagon and
they're not really understanding their
way through the problem. And I think you
know the big brains in this room and the
network that you folks have, a really
key component of being able to succeed
is to understand your way through that
problem. So that was a hype example
around Agentic that I was thankfully
able to help this company through. Other
recent hype examples you've probably
seen the software engineering is dead.
My personal favorite Hollywood is dead
or AGI by year end. Um, I was in Saudi
Arabia this time last year at a thing
called the FI and it was a dinner at the
FI and I sat beside the CEO of a company
who I'm not going to name, but this was
a CEO of a generative AI company and at
that time he was showing everybody
around the table this thing that he'd
done where it was text to video and he
could put in a text prompt and get video
out of the prompt and get about six
seconds worth of video out of it. Year
ago, that was I beg you pardon two years
ago. two years ago that was hot stuff.
Nowadays obviously it's quite p anybody
can do it. But he made a comment at that
table and it was a lot of like um media
executives at that table was like by
this time next year from a single prompt
we'll be able to do 90 minutes of video
and uh so bye-bye Hollywood you know
like so the the whole Hollywood is dead
meme I think came out of that. First of
all we can't do 90 minutes even two
years later from a prompt and even if
you did what kind of prompt would be
able to tell you a full story of a movie
right? So this type of hype leads to
engagement. This type of hype leads to
attention. But my encouragement to you
is to peel that apart. Look for the
signal. Ask the why question. Ask the
what question and move on from there.
So becoming that trusted adviser,
world's drowning in hype. How do you do
it? Look at the trends, evaluate them
objectively. Look at the genuine
opportunities that are out there.
There are fashionable distractions. I
don't know what the next one is going to
be, but there are these distractions
that are out there that will get you
lots of engagement on social media.
Ignore them and ignore the people that
are leaning into them. And then really
lean into your skills about explaining
technical reality to leadership. Uh, one
skill that one person coached me in once
that I thought was really interesting
because it sounded wrong but it ended up
being right was whenever you see
something like this, try to figure out
how to make it as mundane as possible.
When you can figure out how to make it
as mundane as possible, then you really
begin to build the grounding for being
able to explain it in detail in ways
that people need to understand, right?
Like if I you you go and you look at you
know I think Gemini 3 um was released
today but there were leaks earlier this
week and one person kind of leaked that
I built a Minecraft clone and a prompt
you know that kind of stuff. This is the
opposite of mundane, right? This was
like massively hyping the thing,
massively showing, and of course they
didn't. They built a flashy demo. They
didn't really build a Minecraft clone.
But the idea here is if you can peel
that apart to like, okay, how do I think
about what are the mundane things that
are happening here? Um, the the one that
I've been working with a lot recently is
video. So text to video prompts, as I've
mentioned, instead of the magical you
can do whatever you want, all nice and
fluffy, Hollywood is dead. What is the
mundane element of doing text to video?
The mundane element of doing text to
video is that when you train a model to
create video from a text prompt, what it
is doing is it's creating a number of
successive frames. And each of those
successive frames is going to be
slightly different from the frame
before. And you've trained a model by
looking at video to say, well, you know,
if in frame one the person's hands like
this, in frame two it's like that, then
you can predict it moves this way if
there's a matching prompt. And suddenly
it's become a little bit more mundane,
but suddenly they begin to understand
it. And then the people who are experts
in that specific field, not the
technical side of it, are now the ones
that will actually be able to come up
and do brilliant things with it.
So that hype navigation strategy, filter
actively, go deep on the fundamentals,
get your slides to work, and then of
course keep your finger on the pulse.
The hardest part of that, I think, is
the third one is really keeping your
finger on the pulse. And that's when you
have to wait into those cess pits of
people like just farming engagement and
really try to figure out the signal from
the noise there. But I think it's really
important for you to be able to do that
to be connected to understand that
reading papers is all very good. The
signal to noise ratio I think in reading
papers is a lot better. But to
understand the landscape that the people
that you are advising, they are the ones
who are waiting in the cesspools of
Twitter and X and LinkedIn and there's
nothing wrong with those platforms in
and of themselves, but the stuff that's
posted on those platforms.
So
overall landscape,
it is ripe with opportunity. Absolutely
ripe with opportunity. Um, so I would
encourage you as Andrew did to continue
learning, to continue digging into what
you can do and to continue building. But
there are risks ahead, right? You know
the have anybody remember the movie
Titanic?
Remember the famous phrase in that
iceberg right ahead. You know, but
immediately before that, there's a scene
in Titanic. If we weren't being filmed,
I would show it, but I can't uh for
copyright reasons, where the two guys up
in the crow's nests are kind of like
freezing and talking. And like the
crow's nest at the top of the ship is
where the spotters would be to spot any
icebergs in front. And go back and watch
the movie again. You'll see the
conversation between these two guys is
that all they're talking about is how
cold they are. Um, and then it cuts away
to the crew of the ship who are like,
"Wait, aren't they supposed to have
binoculars?" you know, and then the crew
was like, "Oh, we left the binoculars
behind in port." That framing the whole
idea was like they were so arrogant in
being able to move forward that they
didn't want to look out for any
particular risks. And even though they
had people whose job it was to look out
for risks, they didn't properly equip or
train them. And that to me is a really
good metaphor for where the AI industry
is today. There are risks in front of
us. Um, those risks, the B- word, the
bubble word you're probably reading in
the news is there are there. Um to me
though the opportunity and the um
the uh the things to think about in
terms of a bubble are most of you
probably don't remember the dot bubble
of the 2000s but if you think about the
dot bubble that was the biggest bubble
in history it burst
but we're still here and the people who
did com rights not only survived they
thrived. Amazon, Google, you know, they
did it right. They understood the
fundamentals of what it was to build
a.com. They understood the fundamentals
of what it was to build a business
on.com. And when the bubble of hype
burst, they didn't go with it. There was
one website, I believe it was pets.com,
that they had the mindset of if you
build it, they will come. They had Super
Bowl commercials around pets.com. They
couldn't handle the traffic that they
got. And that was the kind of site that
when the when the bubble burst, those
were the kind of sites that just
evaporated. So that bubble in AI is
likely coming. There is always a bubble.
So the companies that are doing AI right
are the ones like I said that won't just
you know um avoid the bubble that they
will actually thrive uh postbubble. and
the people who are doing AI right, the
folks in this room who are thinking
about AI and how you bring it to your
company and the advice that you're
giving to your company and leaning into
that in the right way will also be the
ones who not only avoid getting laid off
in the bubble crashes but the what will
be the ones who will thrive through and
after the bubble. So anatomy of any
bubble and what I'm seeing in the AI one
in particular is this kind of pyramid.
At the top is the hype that I've been
talking about. At the bottom is massive
VC investment. I'll be frank, I'm
already seeing that drying up, right?
You know, once upon a time you could go
out with anything that had AI written on
it and get VC investment. Then you could
go out and do anything with an LLM and
get VC investment. Now they're far far
far more cautious. I've been advising a
lot of startups. The amount that they're
getting invested is being scaled back.
Um the uh the stuff that's being
invested in is changing and you know the
you know this the second layer down
massive VC investment is already
beginning to vanish. Unrealistic
valuations companies that aren't making
money being valued massively high. We
all know who they are. You know we're
beginning to see those unrealistic
valuations being fed off of that hype.
me too products where somebody does
something and it's successful and
everybody jumps on the bandwagon. We're
also seeing them everywhere. We saw them
throughout the dotcom bubble, right? And
then right at the bottom is that real
value. You know, I probably shouldn't
have done a the triangle like this. It
should be more an upside down triangle,
right? Because you know the uh the real
value here is small. I vibe coded these
slides into existence. So this is one of
the technical debt I took on um you know
so the but the real value there that
that kernel of value is there and the
ones that build for that will be the
ones that survive.
So
the direction that I see the AI industry
going in um and the direction that I
encourage you to start thinking about
your skills in is really over the next
five years there's going to be a
bifurcation. Okay, it's gonna I'm just
gonna be ornery in how I describe them
as big and small, right? Big AI will be
what we see today with the large
language models getting bigger in the in
the desire to drive towards AGI. The
Geminis, the clouds, the open AIs of the
world are going to continue to drive
bigger and bigger is better in the
mindset of those companies towards
achieving AGI or towards achieving
better business value. That's going to
be one side of the branch. The other
side of the branch is I'm going to call
it small. We've all seen open source
models. Um I hate the term open source.
Let me call them open weights or let me
call them self-hostable
uh models are becoming they're exploding
onto the landscape. Um I read an article
recently about Y Combinator that 80% of
the companies in Y Combinator we're
using small models from China in
particular. Um so the Chinese models um
in particular are doing really well
probably because of the overall
landscape there not leaning into the
large models the same way as the west
is. Um I see that bifurcation happening.
China I think has that head start on the
smaller models that may last it may not
does I don't know. Uh but the point is
we're heading in that particular
direction of I'm going to call them
instead of big and small now models that
are hosted on your behalf by somebody
else like a GPT or a Gemini or a Claude
or models that you can host yourself for
your own needs. Um as this side is right
now is underserved. This bubble may
burst. This one right now is underserved
and that this bubble will be later on.
Um, and the major skills that I can see
developers needing over the next two to
three years on this side of the fence
will be fine-tuning.
Uh, so the ability to take an open
source model and fine-tune it for
particular downstream tasks. Let me give
one concrete example of that that I've
personally experienced. I work a lot in
Hollywood and I've worked a lot with
studios making movies and um, one studio
in particular I was lucky enough to sell
a movie to. It's still in
pre-production. It'll probably be in
pre-production forever. Um, but one of
the things I learned as part of that
process was IP in studios is so
protected, it's not even funny. Um, go
and Google for James Cameron who created
Avatar and the lawsuits that he's
involved in of this person who
apparently sent him a story many years
ago about blue aliens and is now suing
him for billions of dollars because
obviously there were blue aliens in
Avatar. Um the level of IP protection in
Hollywood is insane. The opportunity
with large language models is equally
insane. Um a lot of the focus is on
large language models for creation, for
storytelling, for rendering and all
that. But actually the major opportunity
that they have is actually for analysis.
Um to take a look at um synopsies of
movies and find out what works and what
doesn't. Why was this movie a hit and
this one wasn't? What time of year was
this one released and it became
successful and this one wasn't? And with
the margin on movies being razor thin,
that kind of analysis is huge. But in
order to do that kind of analysis, you
need to share the details of your movie
with a large language model and they
will absolutely not do that with a GPT
or a Gemini or whatever because they're
now sharing their IP with a third party.
Enter small models where they can
self-host their their own small model
and they are getting smarter and
smarter. the 7B uh model of today is as
smart as the 50B model of yesterday. You
know, a year from now, the 7B model of a
year from now will be as smart as the
300B uh model of yesterday year. Um so
they're moving in that direction of
building using small self-hosted models
which they can then fine-tune on
downstream tasks. Similar with other
things where privacy is important, law
offices, medical offices, all of those
kind of things. So those type of skills
are fundamentally important going
forward. Um, so that's the bifurcation
that I'm seeing happening in AI. The
sooner bubble, I think is in the bigger
nonself-hosted.
The later bubble is in the smaller
self-hosted. But either way, for you for
your career to avoid the impact of any
bubble bursting, focus on the
fundamentals, build those real
solutions, understand the business side,
and most of all, diversify your skills.
Don't be that one-trick pony who who
only knows how to do one thing. I've
worked with brilliant people who are
fantastic at coding a particular API or
particular framework and then the
industry moved on and they got left
behind.
Okay. So yeah um when bubbles burst that
overall fallout kind of spoken about it
a little bit already funding evaporates
hiring freezes become layoffs projects
get cancelled and talent floods the
market. Yep.
>> Quick questions.
I have heard a lot about how
and they're very like specific about
like they want people who are like very
specific about a problem that they have.
So they require people to be like
basically put on that one.
So
how do you think how how is it more
important to
like diversify skills versus like
actually like focusing on for example
LLM versus like computer vision or like
very specific
Right. So I mean I think so the question
was around Nvidia in particular are
hiring for a very specific very narrow
scenario. So then the question is how
important is it for you to become an
expert in a narrow scenario versus
divers diversifying your skills. I would
always argue it's still better to
diversify your skills. Um because that
one narrow scenario is only that one
narrow scenario and you're putting all
your eggs into one basket. Nvidia would
be a fantastic company to work for.
Nothing against them in any way. But if
you put all of your eggs into that
basket and you don't get it then what
right? So I think the idea of really
being able to
if you are [clears throat] passionate
about a thing to be very deep in that
thing is very very good but to only be
able to do that thing I think you know I
would always encourage to be diversified
and when I say diversified like you were
saying LLMs or computer vision or
anything like that I think that mean
that's one part of it but it's like that
knowledge of models and how to use them
to me is a uni skill. it the the
diversification of skills is breaking
outside of that also to be able to think
okay what about building applications on
top of these what does scaling an
application look like what does software
engineering in this case look like what
about user experience and user
experience skills because it's all very
well to build a beautiful application
but if nobody can use it I'm looking at
you Microsoft office uh you know that
they you know there's like there's stuff
like that that you just you know that's
what I really mean about diversifying
beyond so even in that like mono example
with Nvidia to be able to break out of
like that one particular example, but to
show skills in other areas that are of
value, I think is really important.
Okay. Um, as we're just running a little
bit, so yeah, I just wanted to I've kind
of gone into it a little bit already,
but I'm a massive advocate for small AI.
I really do believe small AI is the next
big thing. Uh, because we're moving into
a world, and this is part of the job
that I do at ARM, is we're kind of
moving into a world of like AI
everywhere all at once. Um, so there's a
traditional, and it's interesting you
just brought up Nvidia because there's a
traditional conception that compute
platforms are CPU plus GPU when it comes
to AI, but that's also changing, right?
CPU, general purpose, GPU specialists.
But for example, in mobile space, um,
there's massive innovation being done
with a technology calledme, scalable
matrix extensions. And what is all about
is really allowing you to bring AI
workloads and put them on the CPU. uh
the the the front runners in this are a
couple of Chinese phone vendors um uh
Vivo and OPPO who've just recently
released phones with theme enabled chips
and what's magical about these is that a
they don't need to have a separate
external chip drawing extra power taking
up extra footprint space just to be able
to run AI workloads and b the CPU of
course being a low power pulling thing
being able to run AI workloads on that
they've been able to build interesting
new scenarios and if I talk about one in
particular
Uh there's a company called Alipe and
Alip Pay had an application where you
would and we've all seen these apps
where you can go through your
photographs and you can search for a
particular thing, you know, places I ate
sushi or something along those lines and
use that to create a slideshow. All of
those require a back-end service. So
your photographs are hosted on Google
Photos or Apple Photos or something like
that. And that backend service runs the
model that you can search against it and
be able to do the assembly of them. What
Alipe wanted to do was like say there
are three problems with this. Problem
number one, privacy. You have to share
your photos with a third party. Problem
number two, latency. You got to upload
those photos. You got to send the thing.
You got to have the backend do the
thing. And then you got to download the
results from the thing. And then number
three is building that cloud service and
standing that up cost time and money. So
if they could move all of this onto the
device itself, now the idea was they
they could run a model on the device
that searches the photos on the device.
You don't have the latency and business
perspective. They're now saving the
money on stand on creating this standup
service. They now have AI running on the
CPU in order to be able to do that.
Apple are also people who've invested
heavily in this scalable matrix
extensions. You see whenever they talk
about if you've ever watched WWDC or
anything like that when they talk about
the new A series chips and M series
chips about the neural cores and those
kind of things in them that's part of
the idea. So to think about breaking
that you know habit that we've gotten
into uh where you need a GPU to be able
to do AI is part of the trend that the
world is heading in. Apple are probably
one of the leaders in that. I'm very
very bullish on Apple and Apple
intelligence as a result and um from the
AI perspective and you know seeing that
trend and following that vector to its
logical conclusion we're as models are
getting smaller embedded intelligence
getting everywhere isn't a pipe dream it
isn't sci-fi anymore it's going to be a
reality that we'll be seeing very very
shortly so that idea of that convergence
of AI because of the ability of smaller
models getting smarter and lower powered
devices being able to run them. We see
that convergence hitting and I see
massive opportunity there.
So um one last part and just going back
to agents for a moment. I think you know
the one thing that I always say is like
a hidden part of artificial intelligence
is really what I like to call artificial
understanding. And when you can start
using models to understand things on
your behalf and when they understand
them on your behalf to be able to craft
from that understanding new things you
can actually develop superpowers where
you're far more effective than ever
before. Be that creating code or
creating other things. And I'm going to
give one quick demo just so we can wrap
up. Um, and I was talking earlier about
generating video.
So, uh, this picture is Whoops.
Sorry, the connection here is not very
good. I lost it. So, here we go. This
picture here is actually of my son
playing ice hockey. And I took this
picture and I was saying, "Okay, I think
I'm very good at prompting." And I wrote
a nice prompt for this picture to get
him. He's in the middle of taking a
slapshot. He's got some beautiful flex
on his stick. And I asked it like,
"Okay, it's a prompt like you know him
scoring a goal. What do you think
happened?
Should we Should we watch? Let's see if
it works.
Ah, this was the wrong video, but it
still shows the same idea. Um, because
of poor prompting or because of poor
understanding of my intent, if I talk
about it in aic senses, the arena that
he was in, which is a practice arena and
doesn't have any people in it. Sorry,
pause it. Um,
if I just rewind to here,
and if we look up in this top right hand
corner here, this is basically where
they store all the garbage. Um, but the
AI didn't know that, had no idea of it,
so assumed it was a full arena and it
started painting people in. And even
though he shot a mile wide, everybody
cheers and somehow he has two sticks in
his hand instead of one and they forgot
his name. Right? So, I did not go
through an agentic workflow to do this.
I did not go through the steps of a
understand intent b once you understand
my intent understand the tools that are
available to you in this case it's v and
understand the intricacies of using vo
um make a plan of how to use them make a
plan of how to build a prompt for them
and then use them and then reflect so
I'm kind of I've been advising a startup
um that is working on movie creation
using AI and I want to show you a little
sample here of a movie that been working
on with them where the whole idea A is
like if you want to have performances
out of virtual actors and actresses, you
need to have emotion, right? You need to
be able to convey that emotion and you
also need to be able to put that emotion
in the context of the entire story
because when you create a video from a
prompt, you're creating an 8-second
snippet. That 8-second snippet needs to
know what's going on in the rest of the
story, right? So, if I show this one for
a moment, and it's a little wooden at
the moment. It's not really working
perfectly. I have professional actors
who are friends who are advising me on
this and they laughed at the
performances. But try to view it through
the difference that we had from an
unagentic prompt with the hockey player
to this one.
Let's hopefully we can hear it.
I guess I can do the pub quiz after all.
They just shut me down. I'm so close.
But they wouldn't listen.
>> I won't.
>> They never listen.
So like here's the idea of like again
just thinking in terms of agentic as I
was saying earlier on breaking it into
those steps that allowed me to use
exactly the same engine as I was showing
you earlier on that fails to be able to
show something that works and is able to
do [music] things like portraying
emotion that I just spoke about. So I
know we're a little bit over time so
sorry about that. I can take any
questions if anybody has any. I see
Andrew is here as well. He's at the
back. And I just really want to say
thank you so much for your attention. I
really appreciate it.
[applause]
>> Yep.
Y.
>> It's a great question. Just to repeat
for the video, how much of the
improvement is from the use of an
agentic workflow versus just lack of
hockey stuff in the training set for the
failed one? Um, I not comparing like to
likes, so just using my gut. Um, when I
looked at when I broke this down into
the workflow that said, "Okay, I created
scenes like this one and they were awful
when I just did it directly for myself
um with no basis, no agentic, no
artificial understanding." And when I
broke it down into the steps where it's
like, okay, in this scene the girl is
sitting on the bench and she's upset and
the person is talking to her and he
wants to comfort her. um feeding that to
a large language model along with the
entire story and along with the
constraints that I had where the shot
has to be 8 seconds long, clear dialogue
and all of those kind of thing. And then
to understand my intent from that one,
the LLM ended up expressing a prompt
that was far more loquacious than I ever
would have, that was far more
descriptive than I ever would have. The
LLM had understanding of what makes a
good shot, what makes a good angle, what
makes good emotion far more than I would
have I could spend hours trying to
describe it. So that first step in the
agentic flow of it doing that for me and
understanding my intent was huge. The
second step then is I you know the tools
that it's going to use. So I explicitly
said which video engine I'm going to be
using. I was using Gemini as the LLM and
hopefully Gemini is familiar with VO you
know that kind of stuff. So to
understand the idiosyncrasies of doing
things with VO what I learned like for
example VO is very bad at doing high
action scenes but is very good at doing
slow camera polls to do emotion as you
saw in this case. So the LLM knew that
from me declaring I was using that as a
tool and then further it built a prompt
and then further refined the prompt from
that and then the third part actually
using the tool to actually generate it
for me. Generating a video with
something like VO costs I think between
two and three dollars to generate like
four videos in credits. So the last
thing I want to do is generate lots and
lots and lots and lots of videos and
throw good money after bad. But all of
that token spend that I did earlier on
to understand my intent and then to make
the plan for using the agent was saved
in the back end where it got it right
like you know maybe not get it right
first time but would very rarely take
more than two or three tries to get
something that was really really nice.
So I think you know without com
comparing like with like I do think that
plan of action and going through a
workflow like that worked very very
well.
Any other
questions, thoughts, comments? Yep. Up
at the back.
>> What has surprised me the most about the
AI industry over the years? Oh, that's a
good one. Um, I think what has surprised
me the most, um, and it probably
shouldn't have surprised me is how much
hype took over. Um, I actually I
honestly thought a lot of people who are
in important decision-making roles and
that kind of thing would be able to see
the signal better than they did. Um and
I think the other part was that the um
the desire to make immediate profits as
opposed to long-term gains also
surprised me a lot. Um let me share one
story um in that space was one of the
things that after we Andrew and I taught
the TensorFlow specializations on
Corsera and after that Google launched a
professional certificate where the idea
of this professional certificate was we'
give a rigorous exam and at the end of
the rigorous exam if you got the
certificate um it was a high prestige
thing that would help you find work and
particularly at the time when TensorFlow
was a very highly demanded skill in just
get work. Um, running that program cost
Google $100,000 a year. Okay, drop in
the bucket. Not a lot of money. Um, the
goodwill that came out of it was
immense. Um I can tell two story I'll
tell one story very quickly was there
was a young man um and he went public in
some like advertising stuff that with
Google that he lived in Syria uh and we
all know there was a huge civil war in
Syria over the last few years and he got
the TensorFlow certificate. He was one
of the first in Syria to get it and it
lifted him out of poverty where he was
able to move to Germany and get work at
a major German firm and I but I met him
at an event in Amsterdam where he told
me his story and now because of like the
job that he had in this German firm he's
able to support his family back home um
and move them out of the war torn zone
into a peaceful zone all because he got
this like AI thing right and there were
countless stories like that um very
inspirational, very beautiful stories.
But the thing that surprised me then was
uh sometimes the lack of investment in
that where there was no revenue being
generated for the company out of that.
We deliberately um kept it revenue
neutral so that the price of the exams
could go down. We wanted it to self-
sustain. It ended up not being revenue
neutral. It ended up costing the company
about 100,000 to 150,000 a year. So they
canned it, you know, and it's a shame
because of all the potential goodwill
that can come out of something like
that. But I think those would be the two
that immediately jumped to mind that
have surprised me the most. Um, and then
I guess the one other part that I would
say is the people who've been able to be
very successful with AI
who you wouldn't think would be the ones
that would be successful with AI has
always been inspirational to me. So
allow me one more story. I have a good
friend. I showed ice hockey a moment
ago. I have a good friend who is a
former professional ice hockey player.
And any ice hockey fans here? Okay. You
know, it's a kind of a brutal sport,
right? You see a lot of fighting and a
lot of stuff on the ice. And he dropped
out of school when he was 13 years old
to focus on skating. And he will always
tell everybody that he's the dumbest
person alive cuz he's uneducated. He and
I are complete opposites, you know,
that's why we get on so well. And uh he
retired from ice hockey because of
concussion issues. And he now runs a
nonprofit uh the ice rinks for
nonprofit.
And about three years ago, um, we were
having a beer and he was like, "So tell
me about AI and tell me about this chat
GPT thing. Is it any good?" And I was
like, you know, just sharing the whole
thing. Yes, it's good. And all that kind
of stuff. And it was obviously a loaded
question and I didn't know why. But part
of his job um at his nonprofit is that
every quarter he has to present to the
board of directors the results of the
operations so that they can be funded
properly because even though they're a
nonprofit, they still need money to
operate. and he was spending upwards of
$150,000 a year to bring in consultants
to kind of pull the data from all of the
different sources they were pulling data
from. There's like machines in what's
called the pump room that has a
compressor that cools the ice and there
were spreadsheets and there was accounts
and all this kind of stuff and he was
not techsavvy in any way and but he like
needed to process all this data. So he
did an experiment where he got Chachi PT
to do it. And this was the loaded
question like asking me was it any good.
And so we talked through it a little bit
and then he told me why. And so I took a
look at the results because he was
uploading spreadsheets, he was uploading
PDFs and all this kind of thing and
getting it to assemble in a report. It
takes him now about two hours to do the
report himself with chat pt and it
worked and it worked brilliantly and
that 150,000 a year that he's saving on
consulting is now going to uh
underprivileged kids right for hockey
equipment for ice skating equipment for
lessons and all of that kind of thing.
So, it was taken out of the hands of an
expensive consulting company and put
into the hands of people uh because of
this guy and he says he's the dumbest
person alive, you know, but I hope he's
not watching this video. Uh but and he's
like, you know, but he and I told him
afterwards that congratulations, you're
now a developer, right? and he didn't
like that. But, [laughter] you know, but
it it's like surprises like that that
the superpowers that were handed to
somebody like him that he's not
technical in any way, but he was able to
effectively build a solution that saved
his nonprofit $100 to $150,000 a year.
And like things like that are always
surprising me in a very pleasant way.
>> Yep. Sorry, I'll get to you next. Sorry.
Yeah.
>> I thinkers
like us It's easy. It's easier to
because we can understand what signal is
from
this knowledge like
>> Yep. So just to repeat the question for
the video for engineers like us
sometimes it's easy to navigate the hype
to see the signal from the noise but
what about people you know who don't
have the same training as us? Um I think
that's our opportunity to be trusted
advisers for them. Um and to really help
them through that to understand it. Um,
I think the biggest part in the hype
story right now is just understanding
the reward mechanism, right? You know,
the everything rewards engagement rather
than actual substance. And the the to me
step one is seeing through that like the
story I just told about my friend you
know he seen all this kind of stuff but
he wasn't willing to bet his career on
it you know but he needed like that kind
of advice around it and to kind of start
peeling apart what he had done and what
he did right and what he did wrong and
you know so that positioning ourselves
to be trusted adviserss by not leaning
into the same mistakes that the
untrained people may be leaning into I
think is the key to that. Um, and you
know, just understanding that the
average person is generally very
intelligent, even if they may not be
experts in a specific domain, and to key
in on that intelligence and help them to
to to foster and to grow that in, you
know, um, and navigate them through the
parts where they'll have difficulty and
let them shine in what they're very very
good at.
>> All right. Over here, there was one.
>> I have a question for
scientific research.
>> Okay.
to get your perspective on where you
think it is a good idea and
so um AI and machine learning for
scientific research where is it a good
idea and where should you be cautious um
oh uh I my initial gut check would be I
think it's always a good idea right um I
think you know there's there's no harm
in using the tools that you have
available to to you but to always to
just double check your results and
double check your expectations against
the grounded reality. Um, I've uh always
been a fan of using automation in
research as much as possible. My
undergraduate was physics uh many many
years ago and I was actually very
successful in the lab because I usually
automated things through a computer that
other people did handwriting and pen and
paper with so I could move quickly. So I
know I'm biased in that regard, but I
would say like for most research for the
most part I think you know use the most
powerful tools you have available but
check your expectations.
Little story actually on that side was
um uh trivia question. Poorest country
in Western Europe anybody know
>> what's that?
>> Western Europe is Wales. So uh I
actually did my undergraduate in Wales
and I went back to do some lectures in
the university there and um I met with a
researcher there and he was doing
research into brain cancer um using
computer imagery and using various types
of computer imagery and I asked him
what's the biggest problem that you have
what's the biggest blocker for your
research and this is about eight years
ago and his answer was access to a GPU
and uh cuz like for him to be able to
train his models and run his models, he
needed to be able to access a GPU. And
uh the department that he was in had one
GPU between 10 researchers, which meant
that everybody got it for half a day,
right? Monday through Friday. And his
half a day was Tuesday afternoon. So in
his case, he would spend the entire time
that wasn't Tuesday afternoon preparing
everything for his model run or his
model training or everything like that.
And then Tuesday afternoon once he had
access to the GPU, then he would do the
training, right? And then he would hope
that in that time that he would train
his model and he would get the results
that he wanted. Otherwise, he'd have to
wait a week, you know, to get access to
the GPU again. Uh, and then I showed him
Google Collab, right? Had anybody ever
used Google Collab, right? And you can
have a GPU in the cloud for free with
that kind of thing. And the poor guy's
brain melted, right? Um, that, you know,
because I took out my phone and I showed
him a notebook running on my phone and
Google Collab and training it on that
and it changed everything for him
research-wise. Um and you know now it
was a case of and this was with free
collab he had much more than he had with
his shared GPU. So I think you know for
someone like him you know machine
learning was an important part of his
research but he was so gated on it that
the ability to widen access to that
ended up like really really advancing
his research. I don't know where it
ended up. I don't know what he has done.
It has been a few years since then but
you know that story just came to mind
when you asked the question.
Any more questions? Any feel free to ask
me anything.
Oh yeah, at the front here
force of sociality or sociality.
>> So can AI be a force of social equality
or social inequality? Um I think the
answer to that is yes. It can be both
and it can be neither. I mean I think
that ultimately the idea is that if in
my opinion any tool can be used for any
means. So the important thing is to
educate and inspire people towards using
things for the correct means. Um there's
only so much governance can be applied
and sometimes governance can cause more
problems than it solves. Um, so I always
love to live my life by assuming good
intent but preparing for bad intent. And
in the case of AI, I don't think there's
any difference there that everything
that I would do and everything that I
would advise is assuming good intent
that people would use it for good
things, but also to be prepared for it
to be misused. Um, the bad examples that
I showed earlier on I think were good
intent rather than bad intent. Um, and
most mistakes that I see like that are
good intent being used mistakenly as
opposed to bad intent. But I would say
that's the only mantra that I can the
only advice that I can give in that kind
of thing is always assume good intent
but prepare for bad intent.
The AI itself has no choice, right? It's
how people use it.
Andrew, did you want closing comments or
>> I think they were running
All right. Thank you, Andrew. Thanks,
[applause]